Guide to the Pierson and Alice Ostrow Papers TAM.288
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Pierson and Alice Ostrow Papers
1928-1993
1930-1948
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Ostrow, Pierson, 1914-1967
Ostrow, Alice Scardino, 1915-2001
Gammel, Dani Danzig
TAM.288
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Pierson Ostrow (1914-1967) and Alice Scardino Ostrow (1915-2001) were socialist and progressive activists. Both were born and raised in Philadelphia, and they met there as students. They joined the Young People's Socialist League (YPSL) and became members of the Socialist Party by the early 1930s. After marrying they moved to Newark, New Jersey. In 1948 Alice Ostrow ran on the Socialist Party ticket for New Jersey's 12th Congressional district. Mr. Ostrow was a philatelic dealer and real estate appraiser, and in the latter capacity was active in the campaign for Vermont's fair housing law, passed in 1967 (the Ostrow's had moved to Vermont in 1955). In Newark, Alice Ostrow worked for the IRS and was legislative representative of the Federation of Federal Employees. She also worked for the Communications Workers of America and organized New Jersey Tenants for Rent Control. After her husband's death, Ms. Ostrow moved to New York City where she was active in the American Civil Liberties Union, the National Association for the Advancement of Colored Peoples, the Workers Defense League, and Americans for Democratic Action. The collection contains unpublished writings of Pierson Ostrow (student essays, poetry, political essays, and a play), files (containing internal documents, printed ephemera and publications) on the Socialist Party and YPSL, both nationally and in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania and Newark, New Jersey (including one on Alice Ostrow's Congressional campaign), files on the American Youth Congress, Camp Arcola (a Federal Emergency Relief Administration camp fro unemployed women in Arcola, PA), the Junior International League of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, the Pennsylvania Committee for Total Disarmament, a scrapbook (clippings and writings), and individual letters to Pierson Ostrow from Harry Laidler, Upton Sinclair and Girolamo Valenti.
Box 1
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Dani Ostrow Danzig Gammel in 2002 and 2014. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2002.019 and 2014.148.
Historical/Biographical Note
Pierson Ostrow (1914-1967) and Alice Scardino Ostrow (1915-2001) were socialist and progressive activists. Both were born and raised in Philadelphia, and they met there as students. They joined the Young People's Socialist League (YPSL) and became members of the Socialist Party by the early 1930s. After marrying they moved to Newark, New Jersey. In 1948 Alice Ostrow ran on the Socialist Party ticket for New Jersey's 12th Congressional district. Mr. Ostrow was a philatelic dealer and real estate appraiser, and in the latter capacity was active in the campaign for Vermont's fair housing law, passed in 1967 (the Ostrows had moved to Vermont in 1955). In Newark, Alice Ostrow worked for the IRS and was legislative representative of the Federation of Federal Employees. She also worked for the Communications Workers of America and organized New Jersey Tenants for Rent Control. After her husband's death, Ms. Ostrow moved to New York City where she was active in the American Civil Liberties Union, the National Association for the Advancement of Colored Peoples, the Workers Defense League, and Americans for Democratic Action.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Pierson and Alice Ostrow Photographs (Photos 276)
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains unpublished writings of Pierson Ostrow (student essays, poetry, political essays, and a play), files (containing internal documents, printed ephemera and publications) on the Socialist Party and YPSL, both nationally and in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania and Newark, New Jersey (including one on Alice Ostrow's Congressional campaign), files on the American Youth Congress, Camp Arcola (a Federal Emergency Relief Administration camp fro unemployed women in Arcola, PA), the Junior International League of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, the Pennsylvania Committee for Total Disarmament, a scrapbook (clippings and writings), and individual letters to Pierson Ostrow from Harry Laidler, Upton Sinclair and Girolamo Valenti.
Socialists -- United States.; Socialism and youth -- United States.; Socialism |z Pennsylvania |z Philadelphia.; Socialism |z New Jersey |z Newark.; Young People's Socialist League; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; Socialist Party (U.S.); Ostrow, Pierson, 1914-1967; Ostrow, Alice Scardino, 1915-2001; Socialist Party of New Jersey; Socialist Party of Pennsylvania; Valenti, Girolamo; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968; Gammel, Dani Danzig
- American Youth Congress, Feb. 19-21, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Camp Arcola, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Camp Arcola: Photographs (photocopies; originals in Non-Print collection), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- East Pennsylvania Youth Congress, Feb. 19-21, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Emergency Relief Board of Pennsylvania: "White Collar Review", 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Essay: "On the Share-the-Work Movement" (unsigned), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Fantasia," Pierson Ostrow, December 15, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Federal Theater (WPA): "It Can't Happen Here" (program), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Holmes, John Haynes (letter to Pierson Ostrow), 1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Junior International League of Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, 1931-1936 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- League for Industrial Democracy (Harry Laidler letter to Pierson Ostrow), 1933 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- National Recovery Administration, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Ostrow, Alice Scardino: Biographical and Memorabilia, 1925; 2001 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Ostrow, Pierson: Education, 1931-1935 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Pennsylvania Committee for Total Disarmament, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Play: "Hurrah for the _____, White, and Blue", undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Play: Untitled Typescript (Scene I), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Poetry: P. Ostrow, 1928-1937 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Publications: American Student Union, 1932-1936 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Publications: The Call, Special Debs Section, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Publications: New View (Socialist Party of New Jersey), 1934 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Publications: Socialist Party (Left Wing), 1936 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Publications: Young People's Socialist League (national), 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Publications: Young People's Socialist League, Newark, NJ, 1933-1945 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Publications: Young People's Socialist League, Philadelphia, PA, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Roosevelt, Eleanor: Junior International League Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Scrapbook: Clippings, Typescripts, etc., 1932-1936 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Sinclair, Upton, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Sketches: Pierson Ostrow, 1930-1932 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Socialist Party, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Socialist Party Handbook and Membership Cards, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Socialist Party of New Jersey: Alice Ostrow Congressional Campaign, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Socialist Party: Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Stetin, Sol, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Student Essays: Pierson Ostrow, 1932-1936 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Thomas, Norman, 1933-1968 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Thomas, Norman: Joe Glazer Song (inscribed), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Valenti, Girolamo: Italian Anti-Fascists, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Young People's Socialist League (YPSL): Philadelphia, PA and New Jersey, 1933-1937 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Young People's Socialist League: Reunion, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 40)